Finding Aid of the UW-Milwaukee University Communications & Media Relations Photographs, circa 1900-2014
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
UW-Milwaukee University Communications & Media Relations Photographs, circa 1900-2014
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. University Communications & Media Relations
UWM Archival Collection 200
6.4 cubic ft. (8 boxes) 65 safety film negatives 7,707 digital files (14.4 GB)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Photographic prints, negatives, slides, and digital images pertaining to the activities of the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee (UWM) and its predecessors compiled or created by the office of University Communications & Media Relations. The photographs were created primarily to illustrate the publications of University Communications & Media Relations dating from 1989 to 2014. The collection includes photographs of prominent visitors to campus; accomplished faculty members, students, and alumni; student activities, including the arts, athletic events, and commencement ceremonies; and activities of senior officials from the UWM administration. The collection also includes photographs that document the campuses of UWM and its predecessor institutions, as well as the city of Milwaukee, from circa 1900 to 1986.
The Milwaukee State Teachers College's Publicity Department became the News Bureau by 1952 and the News Services Office in 1953. After the creation of UWM, the Office of News Services was created in 1957 and later placed under the authority of the Assistant Chancellor of University Relations. It was called News Service (1957-1970), News and Publications (1971-1977), Office of News Services (1978-1986), News Services and Publications (1987-1999), and University Communications & Media Relations (2000-present). The office produces news articles, publications, web content and marketing materials on university events, people, achievements and priorities. Publications include UWM Report (1978-2014), UWM Today (1988-2013), and Kenwood (1983-1988).
The collection consists of photographic prints, negatives, slides, and digital images pertaining to the activities of UWM and its predecessors compiled or created by University Communications & Media Relations. The majority of the photographs were taken during the daily activities of publishing the UWM Report and UWM Today (the magazine of the UWM Alumni Association, renamed UWM Alumni in 2013). The photographs primarily provide a chronological record of the university and the greater Milwaukee community between 1987 and 1986. Some of the photographs in the collection were compiled between circa 1900 and 1986, but appear to have been used for features in the publications produced during the bulk date period.
The collection documents university communications regarding such topics as UWM buildings, administrative changes, student activities, athletics, campus events, minority student groups, faculty and student research, alumni accomplishments, and the university's involvement in world affairs. It includes photographs of prominent visitors to campus from 2000 to 2014, including politicians, academics, and authors; photographs of campus buildings; portraits of accomplished faculty members, students, and alumni; snapshots of daily life and student activities on campus, including the arts, athletic events, and commencement ceremonies; and photographs of activities of senior officials from the UWM administration.
This collection was received in, and is organized in, multiple parts. Additional materials have not been physically arranged and interfiled, and researchers may need to consult more than one part of the collection to locate similar materials.
The records are arranged into the following series:
Publication Files, 1987-2014
UWM Report/UWM Today Photos, 1989-2014
Other Publications, 1987-2009
Event Files, 1965-2011
Subject Files, circa 1900-2011
The files in series 1 and 3 are organized alphabetically by folder heading within each series. Files in series 2 are organized approximately reverse-chronologically by date of event.
A spreadsheet with file-level information on the electronic records is available in the Archives department. The spreadsheet contains information on photographer, copyright status, date of creation of digital image, limited description of photo content, image size, file format, file size, and software used to create the files. Additional technical metadata is available; see an archivist for details.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
UW-Milwaukee University Communications & Media Relations Records UWM Archival Collection 134
UW-Milwaukee University Relations Records UWM Archival Collection 96
Administrative/Restriction Information
Electronic records must be accessed in the Archives reading room, and researchers must use access copies of electronic records. There are no other access restrictions on the materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
University Communications & Media Relations transferred the collection (accession 2006-069) in June 2006. University Communications donated additional materials in August 2014 (accession 2014-028) and May 2016 (accession 2015-045).
As of November 15, 2016, all electronic files were accessible on a Intel Core i5-4570 CPU (3.20 GHz, 4 GB RAM) running Windows 7 Enterprise, with Service Pack 1. Windows Picture and Fax Viewer and Adobe Acrobat were used to access the files.
The collection includes records in the following file formats:
Tagged Image File Format [.tif]
JPEG Interchange File Format [.jpg]
Portable Document Format [.pdf]
Portable Network Graphics [.png]
Windows Bitmap [.bmp]
Graphics Interchange Format [.gif]
Adobe Encapsulated PostScript [.eps]
Adobe Illustrator [.ai]
Microsoft Word Document 97-2003 [.doc]
Contents List
- Records, circa 1900-2014, UWM Archival Collection 200; 6.4 cubic ft. (8 boxes) 65 safety negatives 7,707 digital files (14.4 GB)
  - 1. Publications, 1987-2014
    Most of the photographs in this series were taken during the daily activities of publishing the UWM Report and UWM Today from 1989 to 2014. Photographs of interest from both the Report and Today include presidential candidates George W. Bush (2002) and John Kerry (2004), the Rube Goldberg Contest from the summer of 2002, Commencement photos from 2003-2006, Pantherfest, UWM Alumni Association event photos, Panther Prowl, and many UWM sports photographs including the men's basketball Sweet Sixteen trip (2005) and the Horizon League Tournament.
    Also present are photographs from other university publications, such as the View Book, Kenwood, the UWM portion of The University of Wisconsin System Introduction, Panther Family News, Neighbor Notes, Fact Card, and a variety of brochures.
    - A. UWM Report/UWM Today Photos, 1989-2014
      - UWM Report Photographs
        - 1993-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1-33)
        - 1997-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1-48)
        - 2002-2003 (Box 8, Folder 5-7)
        - 2002-2014
      - UWM Today Photographs
        - 1989-2002 (Box 3, Folder 1-33)
        - 2001-2009
        - 2003-2004 (Box 8, Folder 8-11)
    - B. Other Publications, 1987-2009
      - Brochures
        - 1993-2000 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
        - 2006
      - Commemorative Booklet for John H. Schroeder, 1991-1998 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Fact Card
        - 2000-2006 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        - 2005
      - Kenwood Photographs, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
      - Neighbor Notes
        - 2000-2008 (Box 7, Folder 6)
        - 2002-2008
      - News Photographs, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Panther Family News
        - 2004-2008
        - 2004-2009 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - University of Wisconsin System Introduction, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - View Book Photographs
        - circa 1997-2005 (Box 7, Folder 9)
        - 2002-2003 (Box 4, Folder 8)
        - 2009
  - 2. Events, 1965-2011
    Series 2 documents events on campus from 1965 to 2011. Noteworthy are photographs of prominent visitors to campus from 2000 to 2006 including Gloria Steinem, Ralph Nader, Michael Moore, Toni Morrison, Cornel West, Maya Angelou, and Alice Walker. The collection also includes a small number of photographs of Lady Bird Johnson during her 1965 visit to Milwaukee. Also included are photographs of student activities on campus, including the protests of 1970, athletic events (such as the trip of the men's basketball team to the NCAA Sweet Sixteen in 2005), and the inaugurations of Chancellor Nancy Zimpher in 1999 and Chancellor Michael R. Lovell in 2011.
    - Chancellor Lovell Holiday Card, 2011 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Chancellor Michael R. Lovell Inauguration, 2011 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Southeast Wisconsin Energy Tech Research Center, 2009 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Men's Basketball NCAA Sweet Sixteen, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous Events, 2002-2004 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Alumnus Runs with Olympic Torch, 2002 January 5 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Zelazo Dedication, 2002 February 15 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Viennese Ball, 2002 March 9 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Mineta [Norm] at UWM, 2002 April 25 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - East Tower Dedication, 2002 May 6 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Bush, George W. at UWM, 2002 August 14 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - College Connections, UWM and MATC, 2002 December (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Sullivan Molds, 2002 December 6 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Miller Park Agreement, 2001 February 2 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Dorm Under Construction, 2001 April (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Pearl, Bruce, New Men's Basketball Coach, 2001 April 11 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Vietnam Memorial, 2001 May 19 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Regents Meeting at Brewers Park, 2001 June (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Campus Move-In, 2001 September (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Walker, Alice, 2001 October 5 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Provost Welcome, 2000 February 22 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Length of Service Auction, 2000 April (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Goodall, Jane, 2000 April 13 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Angelou, Maya, 2000 May 10 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Regents Meeting/Dynamics of Change Conference, 2000 June 7-9 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Nancy Zimpher at WUWM Studios, 2000 August 1 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Crane Accident, 2000 August 9 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Morrison, Toni, 2000 August 28 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Nader, Ralph and Moore, Michael, 2000 September 20 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - ABC at UWM, 2000 October 3 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Erecting New Campus Signs, 2000 October 26 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Steinem, Gloria, 2000 October 31 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Chancellor's Halloween Tour/School of Allied Health Professions Run, 2000 October 31 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Installing New Banners, 1999 March (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Engaged University Conference, 1999 March 25-26 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Nancy Zimpher Inauguration, 1999 March 26 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Nancy Zimpher's First Day, 1998 August 3 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - UWM Professional Theater Training Program Trip to China, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Muhammad, Khallid Abdul, Visit, 1994 March 21 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - UWM 100th Anniversary, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - UWM Delegation to China, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Hayakawa, S.I., Visit and Protests, 1970 February 14 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Student Protests, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Women in Action, 1966 May (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - New Mascot, Logo, and Fight Song, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Dedication Ceremony of Milwaukee/Downer Marker and UWM Archives Center, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Freshman Frolic, Get Acquainted Evening, and Chancellor's Reception, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Groundbreaking of Fine Arts Building, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Johnson, Lady Bird, Visit to Milwaukee, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - 3. Subject Files, circa 1900-2011
    Series 3 covers a variety of topics relating to campus life from circa 1900 to 2011. Highlights of the series include photographs of historic theaters in the Milwaukee area, UWM's involvement with the early years of the Peace Corps, the launch of the Milwaukee Idea initiative in 1998, and campus aerial shots, 1989-1998. The series also documents the development of campus, from its initial beginnings as Milwaukee Normal School in the "Old Main" building (now Mitchell Hall), to the construction of new administrative, classroom, library, athletic, and arts buildings during the 1960s and 1970s, through the dedication of the Zelazo Center for the Performing Arts in 2002.Images include those of prominent political figures who visited campus, including George W. Bush, and 2004 Democratic primary presidential hopefuls Dennis Kucinich and Howard Dean. Also included are photographs of commencement from 2004 to 20011, American Indian Awareness Days 2004, Pantherfest from 2003 to 2005, UWM events at Miller Park, and some men's and women's basketball games from 2003 to 2006.
    - Activities, 2004 June
    - Aerial Photos, 2001-2008 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
    - AIM Meetings, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Albert Hall, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Alumni Association Photos, 2005
    - American Indian Awareness, 2004 April
    - Art Gallery Images, 2008
    - Arts on Campus, circa 1900-1959 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Athletics
      - 1940-1969 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - 1997 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - 2002 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - 2003-2005 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Baker Field House, circa 1950s (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Basketball
      - 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - 2006 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Beasties at Miller Park, circa 2004
    - Black and Gold Day, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Block Party, 2002
    - Board of Regents, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Board of Visitors, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Bookstore, circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Bush, George W., 2002
    - Business and Industry Fair, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Campus Aerial Shots
      - 1989-1998 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - undated
    - Campus Buildings
      - 1995 and earlier (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - 1996 (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
      - 1999-2002 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - Details, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - Miscellaneous, circa 1970s-1998 (Box 5, Folder 22-23)
    - Campus Elementary School, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Campus People, General, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Campus Scenes
      - circa 1900-1960 (Box 5, Folder 26)
      - 1980s-2000s (Box 5, Folder 27-31)
    - Campus Sculpture, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Campus Signage, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Campus Signs/Flags, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Campus Visitors/Government Officials, circa 1960s-1988 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Career Fair, 2002
    - Celebrities, 2000-2004 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Chancellor Nancy Zimpher, 1998-2003 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Chancellor's Reception, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Cheerleaders, circa 1960s (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Class Reunions, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Clinton-Rose Senior Center, 2004
    - Commencement
      - 1964 (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - 1967 (Box 5, Folder 42)
      - 2000 (Box 5, Folder 43)
      - 2001-2006 (Box 5, Folder 44)
      - 2004-2011
    - Convocation, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Convocation and Commencement, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Davida Icons, 2004
    - Department of Theater Arts, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Displays, 2003-2009 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Distinguished Lecture Series, 2004
    - Downer Avenue Pharmacy, circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Downer Woods, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - E Building, circa 1959 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Engelmann Hall, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Extra Profile Photos, 2003
    - Faculty, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Freshwater Research Brochure, 2007
    - Girls Basketball League Quarterfinals Photos, 2005
    - Harnischfeger Home, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Hartford School, 2008
    - High School Relations Activity, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Historic Theaters, circa 1896-1940s (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Horizon League
      - 2003
      - Tournament Crowd Photos, 2011
    - IBM Lectern, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - International Students, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Keodouangnsy Trip to Thailand and Laos, 2004
    - Klotsche, J. Martin, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Lake Michigan, circa 1900-1990s (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - LearnMore, 2003
    - License Plate Poster, 2009 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - March Madness, 2006
    - Miller Park, 2005-2010
    - Milwaukee
      - 1989-1998 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - 2002 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Milwaukee Idea
      - Launches, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Photographs, 1999-2002 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Video, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Milwaukee Night Sky, 2006
    - Milwaukee Partnership Academy, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Milwaukee Skyline, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Miriam Sushman Negatives, undated, 35 mm safety film negatives (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1896-2005 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - 2000-2005
    - Mitchell Hall, circa 1965-1990 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Music Department Activities, 1964-1972 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Music Therapy, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - NCAA
      - Men, 2005-2006
      - Women, 2006
    - Oceanography, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Odyssey, undated
    - Pantherfest
      - 2002-2005 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - 2003-2005
    - Peace Corps, 1963-1966 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Photo Archive, 1982-2000 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Plenary, 2008-2011
    - Pom Pon Girls, circa 1960s (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - President Harrington and UWM Administration, circa 1960s (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Presidential Candidates, 2004
    - Pritzlaff Home, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Professor Photos, Clark & Pradeep, 2006
    - Prominent Alumni, circa 1916-1990s (Box 6, Folder 25-27)
    - Prominent Non-Alumni, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - River & Fountain Images, 2010
    - Roberto Hernandez Center Photos, 2007
    - Rube Goldberg Contest, 2002
    - Schlesinger, Arthur, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - School of Fine Arts, undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Seasons
      - Fall, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 31)
      - Spring, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 32)
      - Winter, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Student Life
      - 1968 (Box 6, Folder 34)
      - circa 1980-1999 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Students on Campus, 2007
    - Sturgeon, undated
    - Summer Photos, 2010
    - Temple Emanu-El, 1956-2001 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Tree Lighting Ceremony, circa 1960s (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Travel McKinley, undated
    - UWM Adult Guidebook Photos, 2010
    - UWM Bike Photos, 2003
    - UWM Highlights, 2005
    - UWM v. Butler, 2003
    - UW Past Presidents, circa 1890s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - UWM Post Editor, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Versant Photo Shoots, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 40-42)
    - Vevier (George) with African Teachers, undated (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Viennese Ball, 2004
    - Welcome Week
      - 2001-2005 (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - 2005
    - Williams, Ruth, undated
    - World Affairs Institute, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - WUWM-FM Radio Station, undated (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Zelazo Center, undated